Guide to the William Clyde De Vane Papers
Yale University Library
Manuscripts and Archives
William Clyde De Vane papers
1908-1968
MS 1114
De Vane, William Clyde, 1898-1965.
5 linear feet (11 boxes, 1 folio)
Professional papers relating to De Vane's research, teaching, and other activities at Yale University. Included are correspondence, writings, speeches, lecture notes, research materials (particularly on Robert Browning), biographical material, and photographs. The academic papers of his wife, Mabel Phillips De Vane, are also part of the collection. They consist chiefly of essays written while she was a graduate student at Yale University, ca. 1925, together with memorabilia and biographical material.
Manuscripts and Archives Sterling Memorial Library 128 Wall Street P.O. Box 208240 New Haven, CT 06520 Web: http://www.library.yale.edu/mssa/ Email: mssa.assist@yale.edu Phone: (203) 432-1735 Fax: (203) 432-7441
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Milton De Vane, 1980.
Description of the Collection
Professional papers relating to De Vane's research, teaching, and other activities at Yale University. Included are correspondence, writings, speeches, lecture notes, research materials (particularly on Robert Browning), biographical material, and photographs. The academic papers of his wife, Mabel Phillips De Vane, are also part of the collection. They consist chiefly of essays written while she was a graduate student at Yale University, ca. 1925, together with memorabilia and biographical material.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. William C. De Vane. II. Mabel Phillips De Vane. III. Photographs.
Access Terms
Browning, Robert, 1812-1889.; De Vane, Mabel Phillips, 1899-1979.; De Vane, William Clyde, 1898-1965.; Yale University. Curricula.; Yale University. Dept. of English.; Yale University. Faculty.; Educators.; Literature--History and criticism.
Collection Contents
- WILLIAM C. De VANE, 1908-1968, no date; Series I; 3 linear feet (7 boxes)
  Correspondence is arranged primarily by individual correspondent, in alphabetical order. The remainder is arranged alphabetically in general files. Most of the correspondence consists of incoming letters.
  Writings and Speeches is filed chronologically where a date could be assigned. Undated material is filed alphabetically by the title. Untitled and undated material will be found at the end of the section.
  Class Lecture Notes is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  Writings of Others is arranged alphabetically by author.
  Subject Files is arranged in two sections. Robert Browning material, including various types of research material and correspondence, is arranged by type of material. The publications section consists of correspondence, clippings and an unidentified manuscript fragment. It is arranged by type.
  Honors and Citations is arranged chronologically.
  Biographical Material is foldered by type of material, and arranged chronologically.
  Memorabilia is arranged by type of material.
  - Correspondence
    - Angell, James Rowland, 1937, no date (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Carroll, Richard C., 1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Davis, Gladys (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Davis, Herbert, 1937-1963, 1967, no date (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Farrand, Livingston, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Furniss, Edgar S., 1936-1938, no date (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Hemingway, Mary Dimock (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Hemingway, Samuel Burdett, 1937-1939, no date (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Keller, Albert Galloway, 1934-1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - [Menner?], Bob, 1939-1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Nettleton, George H., 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Notestein, Wallace, 1934-1950, no date (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Seymour, Charles, 1937-1939, no date (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Spahr, Mary, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Strunk, W., 1934 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Sterling, J.E. Wallace, 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Thurber, James, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - [Tinker, Chauncey Brewster], 1934-1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - White, E.B. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - White, Katharine S., 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - A - G, 1934-1966, no date (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - H - P, 1934-1966, no date (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - R - W, unidentified, 1934-1966, no date (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Writings and speeches
    - List, 1937-1964, no date (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Published texts, notes and drafts
      - 1933, 1937, 1939, 1940-1945, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 22-26)
      - 1948-1953, 1955-1963 (Box 2, Folder 27-37)
      - 1962-1965 (Box 3, Folder 38-39)
    - Final Report as Dean, manuscript and typescript, two parts, [1963] (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Titles, A - D, no date (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Titles, E - L, no date (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Titles, M - P, no date (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Titles, R - S, no date (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Titles, T - Y, no date (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - George Washington University Radio Forum, 896, magnetic tape, no date (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Untitled, no date (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Notes, no date (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - "Forty years of Education at Yale," Yale Chapter, American Association of University Professors, poster, no date
      See: box 12
  - Class lecture notes
    - Browning and Art, no date (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Metaphysical Poets, no date (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Seventeenth Century English Literature, with assignments
      - Jan - May, n.y. (Box 4, Folder 51)
      - no date (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Literature, 1936, no date (Box 4, Folder 53-54)
  - Writings of others
    - B - C, 1938-1965, no date (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - D - H, 1938-1965, no date (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - J - P, 1938-1965, no date (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - R - W, 1938-1965, no date (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Unidentified play, "The Ghost of Wimpole Street," typescript, no date (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Subject files
    - Robert Browning
      - Correspondence, 1911, 1938-1964, n.d (Box 4, Folder 59)
      - "Elizabeth Barrett Browning," by William C. De Vane, typescript with annotations, no date (Box 4, Folder 60)
      - Copies of reviews of Browning's works, manuscript, no date (Box 5, Folder 61)
      - Book reviews and pamphlets, 1918-1960, no date (Box 5, Folder 62)
      - Comments on a M.L.A. paper on Browning material, includes correspondence, no date (Box 5, Folder 63)
      - Manuscript copies of Browning's correspondence, photostats, notes, no date (Box 5, Folder 64)
      - "The Browning Collections," auction catalogue, 1913 (Box 5, Folder 65)
      - Book sale list, manuscript, no date (Box 5, Folder 66)
      - Manuscript sale catalogue, no date (Box 5, Folder 67)
      - Hodell, Charles W., Old Yellow Book, Source of Browning's The Ring and The Book, 1908 Jul (Box 5, Folder 68)
      - Chronology of Robert Browning's life, 1845-1846, no date
    - Publications
      - Correspondence, 1955-1965 (Box 5, Folder 69)
      - Clippings, 1928-1965 (Box 5, Folder 70)
      - Fragments of unidentified manuscript, no date (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Honors and citations
    - Yale University, Ph.D., 1926
    - Phi Kappa Phi, certificate, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 72)
    - University of Chicago, commencement program, 1937 Aug 27 (Box 5, Folder 73)
    - College of Wooster (Ohio), honorary degree, commencement program, 1944 Oct 21 (Box 5, Folder 74)
    - Washington and Lee University, Doctor of Humane Letters, 1948
    - Washington and Lee University, commencement programs, 1949 Apr 12 (Box 5, Folder 75)
    - Ordre Nationale de la Legion d' Honneur, Chevalier, 1949
    - Chevalier of the Legion of Honor, correspondence, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 76)
    - Furman University, honorary degree, correspondence, printed material, 1950 Jun 5, 1949-1950 (Box 6, Folder 77)
    - Brown University, honorary degree, 1951 Jan 30 (Box 6, Folder 78)
    - University of North Carolina, Doctor of Laws, 1951
    - Middlebury College, honorary degree, 1952 Aug 11 (Box 6, Folder 79)
    - Tufts College, Doctor of Literature, 1953
    - Tufts College, commencement program, correspondence, press release, 1953 May-Jun (Box 6, Folder 80)
    - Loyola University, honorary degree, 1960 Jun 7 (Box 6, Folder 81)
    - Williams College, honorary degree, citation, 1962 Jun 10 (Box 6, Folder 82)
    - Rockford College, honorary degree, 1963 Feb [7] (Box 6, Folder 83)
    - New York University, honorary degree, convocation programs, 1963 Apr 9 (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - University of Toronto, Doctor of Laws, 1963
    - University of Toronto, citation, luncheon speech, 1963 May 31 (Box 6, Folder 85)
    - Harvard University, Doctor of Laws, 1963
    - Harvard University, commencement programs, tickets and invitations, correspondence, photographs, 1963 Jun 3, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 86)
    - Association of American University Professors, citation, no date (Box 6, Folder 87)
  - Biographical material
    - Yale Daily News, articles, 1941-1965 (Box 6, Folder 88)
    - Clippings, 1945-1965, no date (Box 7, Folder 89)
    - Magazine articles
      - 1962-1963 (Box 7, Folder 90)
      - 1963-1965 (Box 7, Folder 91)
    - Notes and draft of sketch, [by Mabel Phillips De Vane], no date (Box 7, Folder 92)
    - Draft of sketch, [by Mabel Phillips De Vane] including some original speech material, post-1965 (Box 7, Folder 93)
    - Draft of sketch, [by Mabel Phillips De Vane], electrostatic copy, research material, post-1965 (Box 7, Folder 94)
    - Notes and drafts of sketch, [by Mabel Phillips De Vane], includes correspondence, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 95)
    - Sketches, data sheets, no date (Box 7, Folder 96)
    - Obituaries, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 97)
    - Memorials, 1965-1968, no date (Box 7, Folder 98)
    - Hendel, Charles W., Dean De Vane and Yale College in War Time, typescript, includes correspondence, 1968 Feb 14 (Box 7, Folder 99)
    - Sketch by Mabel Phillips De Vane, edited electrostatic copy, includes correspondence, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 100)
  - Memorabilia
    - "Hillhouse Avenue From 1809 to 1900," pamphlet, 1907 Oct (Box 7, Folder 101)
    - Yale College, semi-annual examinations, 1918-1919, 1921 (Box 7, Folder 102)
    - Observation Post, Y.C. 1917, no. 11, 1976 Jul (Box 7)
    - Charles Seymour, Jr., "An Ode in Commemoration of the Four Hundredth Anniversary of the Birth of Queen Elizabeth," printed by Carl Purington Rollins Jun, 1933 Jun
    - Membership pins
      - Phi Kappa Phi (Box 7, Folder 103)
      - Pundits (Box 7, Folder 103)
      - Yale Daily News, honorary, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 103)
      - Beta Theta Phi, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 103)
      - Two unidentified pins, no date (Box 7, Folder 103)
- MABEL PHILLIPS De VANE, 1905-1968; Series II; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  There are five major types of material.
  Graduate papers
  Writings and speeches
  Honors and citations (1 folder)
  Biographical material (1 folder)
  Memorabilia
  Graduate papers are arranged alphabetically by title of the papers, as few are dated. Writings and speeches are arranged alphabetically by title. Untitled material is at the end of the section. Memorabilia is arranged by type of material.
  - Graduate papers
    - "Bibliography of the Works of Jonathan Swift," typescript, no date (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - "A Bill for Divorcement,", no date (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Chaucer, short papers on various topics notes, no date (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - "A Consideration of Old English Prose," typescript, no date (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - "Doubtful and Supposititious Works of Jonathan Swift," typescript, no date (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - "Elements of Realism in the Knights' Tale," manuscript, includes notes on Chaucer, no date (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - "Elizabeth Drama, Paper on Thomas Heywood," typescript, 1922 Jun 1 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - English drama, notes, no date (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - "An Essay in the Theory of Poetry," two copies, includes correspondence, 1922 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - "Matthew Prior," typescript, no date (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - "Poems of Jonathan Swift," typescript, draft and notes, no date (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - "Rebecca and Rowena: A Romance upon Romance," typescript, no date (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Royal Society, notes, no date (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Shakespeare, short papers on various topics, notes, 1922 Oct - Dec (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Examination papers, 1923 Apr 18 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Short papers for George H. Nettleton's class, typescripts, no date (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - [Swift, dissertation?], includes correspondence, 1925 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Writings and speeches
    - "And Tell Old Tales," manuscript, notes, no date (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Androcles and the Lion, typescript notes, no date (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - James Rowland Angell (President 1921-1937), typescript, no date (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Anything Can Happen, review, manuscript, no date (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Jane Austen, manuscript notes, no date (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Challenge and Quest, typescript, no date (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Challenge to Change, manuscript, no date (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Gulliver, manuscript draft and notes, no date (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - [Gulliver and Swift], manuscript, no date (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Halley, Edmond, research materials and notes, no date (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - "In Our Day," typescript, no date (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Integrity: J.B. Again, manuscript, no date (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - League of Women Voters, Workshop on Charter Revision, City Planning, including Zoning and Housing, no date (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Maladjustment, manuscript, no date (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - The Mind's Construction, drafts and notes, no date (Box 9, Folder 31)
    - Miscellaneous short pieces, manuscript, no date (Box 9, Folder 32)
    - Overture, manuscript, no date (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - Yale Newcomers speech, manuscripts, no date (Box 9, Folder 34)
    - Yale Then and Now, typescript, no date (Box 9, Folder 35)
    - Yale University Women's Organization, notes for speech, manuscript, no date (Box 9, Folder 36)
    - Untitled speech on idioms, manuscript, no date (Box 9, Folder 37)
    - Introduction to an unidentified paper, manuscript, no date (Box 9, Folder 38)
    - Unidentified notes on the back of galley proofs, no date (Box 9, Folder 39)
    - Unidentified fragments, notes, no date (Box 9, Folder 40)
  - Honors and citations, 1919, 1966, no date (Box 9, Folder 41)
    - Westfield High School, diploma, 1915
    - Wells College, B.A., 1919
    - Yale University, Ph.D., 1925
  - Biographical material, includes correspondence, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 42)
  - Memorabilia
    - Wells College, 1919-1968 (Box 9, Folder 43)
    - Postcards, miscellaneous, 1905-1937, no date (Box 9, Folder 44)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1944-1965; Series III; 1.5 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Photographs are not fully processed. They consist primarily of formal and informal photographs of William C. De Vane. They are arranged by subject.
  - De Vane, William Clyde
    - Formal portraits, no date (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Informal portraits, no date (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Groups, no date (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - De Vane, Mr. Mrs., no date (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - De Vane, Mrs. Mabel Phillips, no date (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Seymour, Charles, 1950 Sep 15 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - World War II, naval photographs, 1944 Jul, no date (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Seascapes taken from the "Vulcania,", 1964 Feb (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Reproductions of Italian art, no date (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Early family
    - [Eckley, Sophia Tuckesmore], no date (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Lincoln, Abraham and son, no date (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Unidentified, no date (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Aerial view of New Haven, ca. WW II? (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Oversize photographs (Box 11)
  - De Vane, William Clyde
    - Formal portrait, no date (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Informal groups, 1949-1965, no date (Box 11, Folder 15)
- OVERSIZE MATERIAL (FOLIO)
  - William C. De Vane
    - Writings and speeches
      - "Forty Years of Education at Yale," Yale Chapter, American Association of University Professors, poster, no date (Box 12)
    - Subject files
      - Chronology of Robert Browning's Life, 1845-1846, no date (Box 12)
    - Honors and citations
      - Yale University, Ph.D., 1926 (Box 12)
      - Washington and Lee University, Doctor of Humane Letters, 1948 (Box 12)
      - Ordre Nationale de la Legion d'Honneur, Chevalier, 1949 (Box 12)
      - University of North Carolina, Doctor of Laws, 1951 (Box 12)
      - Tufts College, Doctor of Literature, 1953 (Box 12)
      - University of Toronto, Doctor of Laws, 1963 (Box 12)
      - Harvard University, Doctor of Laws, 1963 (Box 12)
    - Memorabilia
      - Charles Seymour, Jr., "An Ode in Commemoration of the Four Hundredth Anniversary of the Birth of Queen Elizabeth," printed by Carl Purington Rollins, 1933 Jun (Box 12)
  - Mabel Phillips De Vane
    - Honors, and citations
      - Westfield High School, diploma, 1915 (Box 12)
      - Wells College, B.A., 1919 (Box 12)
      - Yale University, Ph.D., 1925 (Box 12)